[music]
What would you say if I told you that
the cinematography isn't the thing that
makes this sequence in Dune part two so
beautiful? Good song.
>> Don't get me wrong, Greg Fraser's
cinematography is a sight to behold, a
technological marvel, a truly
outstanding accomplishment in the
current landscape of modern film. Okay,
sorry about that. I just get excited
about this sort of thing. But seriously,
there's a lot we can learn from looking
at the various elements that make up
Dune Part 2's stunning eclipse sequence.
things that can help us appreciate how
much storytelling and immersion is
actually going on here. Things that may
help us re-evaluate what we often mean
when we say a film or TV show has
beautiful cinematography.
Because when it comes to June part two,
and more specifically this opening
sequence here, Fraser's undeniably
awesome cinematography seems to be the
main thing everyone talks about. So
today I wanted to talk about some of the
other things that make this sequence
such an impactful and immersive example
of modern cinema scene.
>> Let me show you what I mean by zooming
in on just this series of three shots
here.
Why this moment, you ask? Why not a more
obviously striking moment like this?
Well, that's because this is precisely
the sort of moment that gets overlooked
in these sorts of analyses. And there
are a lot of technical elements we can
discern [music] from just this short
moment. some of which are refreshingly
basic that fully capture the thematic
essence of this sequence in a subtle,
effective and truly multi-ensory manner,
which when we get to the core of things
is what cinema is all about. And it all
boils down to the single recurrent theme
that underpins this [music] entire
sequence.
>> Conflict.
>> That's what these three shots do so
well. They initiate the conflict
artistically and subliminally. That's
often what marks great and transportive
[music] film making. Those small but
intentional subliminal accents
supporting and sculpting our journey as
the audience that aren't very noticeable
but are responsible for a huge amount of
the psychological [music] and emotional
immersion we experience. To illustrate
this a bit more clearly, let's start by
looking at the shot compositions.
The transition between shot one and shot
two marks the moment in which we are
very abruptly shunted from trembling
behind this rock with a panicked Paul
and Jessica into the dominant
perspective of the Harkinan soldiers.
In shot two, we start in a wide shot
framed fairly neutally. And then as we
progress over the crest of the dune, our
perspective transforms quite suddenly
within the same shot into a high angle
wide shot looming over the corpse of
Jamus. In shot three, we're then thrown
into a low angle wide shot, which I
admit isn't anything groundbreaking. In
fact, it's a fairly common approach to
shot sequencing. But with the aim of
establishing conflict visually, in just
20 seconds, [music] we've gone from a
mostly obstructed, shaky, low angled
shot signaling fear and concealment to a
completely open, dynamic, wide shot,
aggressively pushing in and bringing us
into a position of power and
superiority. and then back again to a
low angled shot. Now peering up at the
hearkin and threat from an inferior
position whilst also retreating from its
[music] presence really effectively
re-emphasizing Paul and Jessica's
vulnerability. And it doesn't stop
there. Cutting from shot one to shot two
creates a type of subtle visual whiplash
that's very effective in communicating
the differences in perspective here. The
sudden move from a tight POV shot with
plenty of foreground elements, a
technique known as dirtying the frame
that Greg Fraser frequently uses in his
compositions
to a POV shot that is completely unluded
throws us from a fairly claustrophobic
position to one of total spatial and
aerial freedom. This again subliminally
conveys which point of view here is in
the more commanding position.
Then in shot three, there's the visual
conflict between [music] the cold,
black, artificially clad hearkinins and
the warm, passionate reds and oranges of
Aracus' sands. We can see this
intentionality and conflict baked into
the costume design even more clearly in
shot 3's [music] very deliberate camera
work. Notice how the camera gently pulls
focus in the direction of the leading
lines formed by [music] the sandune,
drawing our eyes downwards in the frame
onto Jamus' body bag, where the tones
and textures of the bag sit in harmony
with the surrounding sands,
strengthening the visual and spiritual
connections between the fman and the
natural beauty of Aruckus' landscape in
a really beautiful way. And speaking of
the landscape, there's even more visual
and arguably cultural conflict
established here. Look at how the
surface of the sand changes between
shots two and three. Maybe this is
intentional, maybe it's not. But now
that we're into the swing of
overanalyzing things,
I feel pretty confident in saying that
this adds yet another dimension to the
visual conflict Denval Nerve and Greg
Fraser are aiming to communicate here.
The hearkening view of Arachus' sands
that sees them as nothing more than a
shapeless source of spice juxtaposed
against the Fman's deep appreciation for
the many intricate complex layers there
are to be found in the desert of
Arachus. Notice also that the glimmers
of spice are not really visible in this
shot that embodies the Fman perspective.
Coincidentally, as our focus shifts to
Jamis, this third shot also incorporates
the sound of the wind gently blowing
across the surface of the sand.
On the one hand, increasing the feeling
of isolation as the hearkinins close in
and on the other once again tying the
Fman people to Iraqus' natural beauty,
this time orally as opposed to visually.
A contrast that is further emphasized by
the abrasive unnatural sound of the
drums that have just ceued the
hearkinins's arrival in shot two
and later by their harsh and mechanized
breathing.
Conflict in every frame and in every
technical component is what these shots
establish so effectively and it carries
on throughout the entire sequence. But
attempting to break down the entire
thing this way could end up being a tad
overwhelming for all of us, especially
me. My aim here was simply to draw
attention to how much we can learn from
a series of shots as small as this.
Shots that may initially seem
insignificant in June part 2's wider
audiovisisual landscape yet in reality
form a fascinating microcosm of the
artistry and technical intent that drive
the tension and conflict underpinning
this entire sequence
from the symbolistic costumes to the
immersive sound design
>> to the rhythmic editing to Han Zimmer's
atmospheric score to Greg Fraser's
highly intentional shot compositions and
innovative approach to natural lighting.
The eclipse setpiece is a true
multi-ensory assault and a particularly
fine example of how smoothly and
consistently VN's June films blend their
thematic approach with their visual and
oral storytelling to create such a
powerfully immersive experience. And
that's really the main takeaway here.
There's not only more to visual
storytelling than cinematography.
There's more to cinema than just
visuals.
Words like photography and
cinematography foreground the visual.
But our experience of cinema has always
been broader than that. As typical
moviegoers, when we characterize the
beauty of films and moments like this as
simply beautiful cinematography, what
we're often responding to isn't just
what we're seeing. It's how image,
sound, rhythm, and performance arrive
together.
>> Call it. [sighs]
It's the incredible synchrony of the
visual and the audible,
the practical and the digital, the
haptic and the dramatic.
In essence, [music] we're responding to
how well every single creative aspect of
a film's production comes together to
craft the entire immersive cinematic
experience.
And that isn't something we experience
with just our eyes. That's what Vilner's
two June films achieve. They're what
happens when the overall cinematic
[music] experience is so immersive, so
multi-ensory, so audiovisisually
layered, so beautiful, it's breathtaking
that it's impossible to pin [music] it
down to just one thing.
So, next time you find yourself using a
[music] sound bite along the lines of,
"Wow, what beautiful cinematography,"
maybe stop for a moment and [music] ask
yourself what it is about the cinema
you've just experienced beyond just the
images that makes that experience seem
so beautiful.
What other audiovisisual components are
you being affected by that you might not
have considered initially?
Food for thought. Thank you very much
for watching.